# TOM CHENG

**DATA SCIENTIST** 

TomHCheng@gmail.com LinkedIn 650.240.6147 GitHub 3701 Alameda de las Pulgas, San Mateo, CA 94403 TableauPublic

## **SUMMARY**

I'm a data scientist specialized in improving business performances through data analysis and sales forecast to find optimal performance criteria for the business to be successful. I have extensive experience in design, implementation, and analysis of data-driven studies/decisions for businesses.

#### **EDUCATION**

Springboard May 2020 - Current

This online data science cohort consists of 500+ hours of intensive curriculums in data science, machine learning, Python, and SQL. Including one guided capstone and two selective capstone projects (see projects).

## San Jose State University

Summer 2010 - Winter 2012

B.A. Psychology 2012

#### **EXPERIENCE**

## **Super Cue Cafe**, *Co-owner*, SF and San Mateo

Jan. 2013 - May 2018

Collected data to forecast sales on a weekly basis to help inventory and staffing efficiently.

Analyze product sales seasonally to help decide on which products to keep, replace, or promote.

Stores staffed according to the forecasts had yearly net gain increasing from 5~20%.

**U.S. Army**, 92A - Logistical Supply Specialist, South Korea

June 2003 - June 2006

This is where I trained to be disciplined. I began as a follower, learned teamwork, and developed leadership.

### **SKILLS**

SOFTWARE AND PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES: Python, Tableau, SQL, MS Excel, MS PowerPoint

DATA ANALYSIS: Pandas, NumPy, statsmodels, Scikit-learn, SciPy

DATA VISUALIZATION: Seaborn, Matplotlib

PREDICTIVE MODELS: ARIMA(X), SARIMA(X), BATS, T/BATS, HWE/SES, VARMA(X)

# **PROJECTS**

### SuperCue Time Series Forecast (click to view)

Sept. 2020 - Nov. 2020

Using Python to clean and implement data to several time series models. I was able to make a model that's able to forecast sales on an hourly level, and capture three seasonality: daily, weekly, and yearly.

## <u>CA House values Exploratory Data Analysis (click to view)</u>

Dec. 2020

After downloading, cleaning, re-organizing data from zillow-research. Here is the exploratory data analysis of California house' estimated values from 1996 Jan to 2020 May.

<u>CA House values forecast with ARMA (click to view)</u> or with <u>VARMA (click to view)</u> Jan. 2020 After testing several different models: SES, ARIMAX, VARMAX, VARMA, TBATS. ARMA had the best overall score. The 1<sup>st</sup> slide shows the accuracy of the prediction, on the 2<sup>nd</sup> slide you get to choose the % gain you're looking for in 5 yrs by BR/zipcode, 3<sup>rd</sup> slide is to check the specific feature's past data and predictions.